Guide to the Ivan J. Ruzicka papers, 1969-1990.
Ruzicka, Ivan J. papers, 1969-1990.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Ivan J. Ruzicka papers, 1969-1990.
4665
Ivan Ruzicka, 1927-
ca. 3.4 cubic ft.
Correspondence, business transaction index notes, and other records.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence, business transaction index notes, technical manuals and articles, and other records of the Ruzickas' bookbinding enterprises in Massachusetts and Florida, especially with Cornell University Library;.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Ivan J. Ruzicka was in born Prague in 1927. He pursued medical studies in Prague and further studies in Semitic languages and philosophy at Charles University. He was also an accomplished musician, working as a symphony orchestra conductor in Cracow, Lodz and Warsaw. He worked ten years as a writer and editor for Radio Prague. He became a master bookbinder through the full European course of training, studying under Josef Vyskocil, founder and first director of the State Laboratory for Restoration at the Charles University Library in Prague and under Willi Tham, head of the Restoration Library of the Saxon Library in Dresden. In 1960, he married Jirina Mares, an outstanding actress-singer in musical theaters in Prague, Warsaw and Vienna. She later became an accomplished professional paper restorer and paper marbler. In 1968, they came to the United States. Since then they have bound and restored books and manuscripts for many American customers, but especially for the Cornell University Library, including many items from the Burgunder Shaw Collection.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence, business transaction index notes, and other records of the Ruzickas' bookbinding enterprises in Massachusetts and Florida, especially with Cornell University Library; also, technical manuals and articles pertaining to the art of bookbinding, book restoration, and conservation; dealers' catalogs, and samples of paper, bindings, cloth, and other appurtenances of bookbinding. Correspondents include many American university librarians, and Bernard F. Burgunder.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Ruzicka, Ivan, 1927-; Burgunder, Bernard F.; Cornell University Library.
Subjects:
Bookbinding.; Books--Conservation and restoration.; Book industries and trade.; Rare books.; Paper--Preservation.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Link to a list of books bound by Ruzicka.
- Bernard F. Burgunder Correspondence, 1970-1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Bernard F. Burgunder Correspondence, 1975-1986 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Cornell Correspondence, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Cornell Correspondence, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
- Andrew D. White - Herbert F.Johnson Museums, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Cornell Correspondence, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Michael Kammen Correspondence, 1971-1981 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Cornell Correspondence, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Cornell Correspondence, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
- Cornell Correspondence, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 13-15)
- Cornell Correspondence, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
- Cornell Correspondence, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
- Cornell Correspondence, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 20-21)
- Cornell Correspondence, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
- Cornell Correspondence, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Cornell Correspondence, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Cornell Correspondence, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Cornell Correspondence, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Cornell Correspondence, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Cornell Correspondence, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Cornell Correspondence, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Cornell Correspondence, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Cornell Correspondence, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Cornell Correspondence, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Cornell Correspondence, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Cornell Correspondence, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Binding receipts, slips, index cards; business with Cornell University, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
- Binding receipts, slips, index cards; business with Cornell University, 1971-1976 (Box 4)
- Binding receipts, slips, index cards; business with Cornell University, 1976-1984 (Box 5)
- Amherst College, 1970-1971 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Andover Harvard Theological Library, 1971-1973 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Stephen Andrus, 1970-1987 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Bamberger, 1970-1971 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Bascom Palmer Eye Institute, 1980-1982 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Bayerische Staatsbibliothek, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Bowdoin College, 1971-1972 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- State University of New York at Buffalo, 1973-1976 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Course, 1972, 1970-1972 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Europe, 1970, 1969-1970 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- University of Florida, 1974-1981 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- General Theological Seminary, 1971-1973 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Guild of Bookworkers, 1968-1975 (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Houghton Library, 1971-1972 (Box 6, Folder 14)
- University of Illinois, 1982-1983 (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Indiana University, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 16)
- Leo, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 17)
- Memphis State University, 1973-1974 (Box 6, Folder 18)
- University of North Carolina, 1977-1979 (Box 6, Folder 19)
- Peabody Museum, 1972-1973 (Box 6, Folder 20)
- University of Pennsylvania, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 21)
- Princeton University, 1970-1981 (Box 6, Folder 22)
- Process Materials Corporation, 1972-1973 (Box 6, Folder 23)
- University of Rochester, 1971-1974 (Box 6, Folder 24)
- University of South Florida, 1976-1985 (Box 6, Folder 25)
- Southern Illinois University, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 26)
- Hans Steinhardt, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 27)
- Syracuse University, 1973-1981 (Box 6, Folder 28)
- Tests, etc., 1969-1975 (Box 6, Folder 29)
- Tests, etc., 1971-1972 (Box 6, Folder 30-31)
- John M. Topham, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 32)
- Twinrocker, 1973-1974 (Box 6, Folder 33)
- Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1970-1980 (Box 6, Folder 34)
- Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1971-1975 (Box 6, Folder 35)
- Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1971-1980 (Box 6, Folder 36)
- Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1975-1982 (Box 6, Folder 37)
- Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1980-1983 (Box 6, Folder 38)
- Ruzicka/Impressions Workshop description and samples, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 39)
- Technical manuals, reports, booklets (Box 7)
- Cloth and paper samples (Box 8-10)
- Articles, Guild of Book Workers Journals, reprints, guestbooks, 1968-1980 (Box 11)
  -some items bound by Ivan Ruzicka